Joseph Cornell
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Diaries, 1941-1973, Series 3:; (boxes 6-10; 5 linear feet)
  - Diary Entries, 1941-1972, 3.1:
    - November1968, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 15-16)
      Includes references to: cellar working phenomenon, Dorothy Coulter visit, "states of mind," eterniday, Gemini, "Anne of Cleves" collage, election of Nixon, Violette le Duc film, the point of this scribbling business, dream "business," "constructive dreaming," and "petering out" with the file collecting.
    - December1968 (Box 9, Folder 17)
      Includes references to: Suzanne de M., Basch's "Prodigal Son," Leila, and semi-hallucinatory kind of dreaming.
    - January1969, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 18-19)
      Includes references to: perplexity regarding diary, book-keeping for box, wanderlusting, Rimbaud, inspiration to construct a new vertical box, uselessness of penning, West Side Story, Debussy cello, and a kind of "mental montage."
    - February1969, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 20-21)
      Includes references to: Carolyn, conversation with Duchamp, hero-worship of Delacroix, object as phenomenon in its own right, "King of Bavaria" from Swann's Way, salient aspects of clearing, new Moon piece, and collage as biographical document.
    - March1969 (Box 9, Folder 22)
      Includes references to: "The Soubrette," "Aurigola" snip-collage, head business, depressing war news, Jeanne Eagels file, "Storm That Never Came" collage, Giraudoux, the pull between cellar work and TV, Eve Propp ("helper," often abbreviated as E. or E.P.) visit, new figurehead boxes, and dreaming in great detail.
    - April1969 (Box 9, Folder 23)
      Includes references to: Sartre's Nausea, Albert Camus, ancient Peruvian clay toy collage, Sue Raney, Arturo B. Michelangeli, "Lunga Durata," Susannah Amanda, and Salamandre film.
    - May1969 (Box 9, Folder 24)
      Includes references to: E.P., "Semester Sunrise" TV show, putting pen to paper with a difference, "back-stage" to dream, "Crystal Palace," "Voyage to the Vermilion Tower," marathon penning, and "Portrait of E."
    - June1969 (Box 9, Folder 25)
      Includes references to: Schubert, Rimbaud, dreams of a spiritual nature, E's Wednesday visits, hallucinatory dreaming, "Spanish Journey," "The Shipwrecked Bouquet," and couch-dreaming.
    - July1969 (Box 9, Folder 26)
      Includes references to: Claire Bloom, summer constellations, Auriga box, E collage, new phase of rapport, "Don't Blow Yr Cool," and "Spanish Journey."
    - August1969, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 27-28)
      Includes references to: E's queries about too many things, "girl without a name," reading in Christian Science Reading Room, "back-yard/cellar window" collage, "under the quince tree" business, Allegra Kent visit, "Chirico Coffee-Pot" collage, Mother's birthday, and visit of Hans Namuth and Anita Tiburzi.
    - September1969, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 29-30)
      Includes references to: "atmosphere" being flavored by mental state, Allegra experience and its aftermath in creativity, visit of P. Adams Sitney, "sleep throughs," "The All-Surprising Light," Howard Hussey, finishing touches on "Little Bear" box, backyard penning, "Tower of Pisa" dream (originally filed in December 1972 file), and Eve.
    - October1969 (Box 9, Folder 31)
      Includes references to: Jan and Eve, Sir Walter Scott's The Bride of Lammermoor, "Little Bear Space Box," two spates of hallucinations, Philippa box, Eve's perceptiveness about Robert's drawing, and bedside penning.
    - November1969, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 32-33)
      Includes references to: "deep well" of the psyche, Brian O'Doherty, Ashbery visit, the Rorschachs, Betsy von Furstenberg, "The Uses of Infinity," and Jeanne Eagels.
    - December1969, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 34-35)
      Includes references to: "flash of Perseus" business, Sunrise Semester, the so-called "nil" experiences, Don Windham visit, Betsy file, "Double Portrait-Winter," Susan Sontag dream, Elizabeth Thode, Joni, and the miracle of Leila.
    - January1970 (Box 9, Folder 36)
      Includes references to: de Severac, Ashbery gift, sensitivity to business world or city scene, Rorschachs, "Jack Dempsey's little girl," Harry Roseman, Leila, and broken connection with Eve.
    - February1970 (Box 9, Folder 37)
      Includes references to: Medici Boy, GC 44 exhumed from the garage, "eye of Nil," Brian O'Doherty, "The Music Box Aviary," Francesca recalled, L. preoccupation, and hallucinatory dreaming.
    - March1970 (Box 9, Folder 38)
      Includes references to: the movie The Chalk Garden, L. visit deferred, Francesca, "Isle of safety," and H. Roseman working.
    - April1970 (Box 9, Folder 39)
      Includes references to: Leila, pensees "green," post-hallucinative state, being in two states at the same time, and Penny Arcade.
    - May1970 (Box 9, Folder 40)
      Includes references to: Eagels, Betsy's voice, Tina in Woolworth's, breaking the "siege," Delacroix, Mallarme, and "reluctant" diary.
    - June1970 (Box 9, Folder 41)
      Includes references to: bizarre hallucination and disorientation of time and space, clutter piled up, Robert's drawings, relationship to past, workings of the psyche, and Carol.
    - July1970 (Box 9, Folder 42)
      Includes references to: Robin, Teeny, Don Windham, "Hotel Abeille," Pasta Parrot, Robert Offergeld, Louis Gottschalk, a new kind of time, and Samson.
    - August1970 (Box 9, Folder 43)
      Includes references to: cabin in Westhampton, passing of Frances Farmer, Dream and Reality, Sandy Simmons, mystical aspect of the girl, and la mignonne.
    - September1970, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 44-45)
      Includes references to: the Dukas phenomenon, "tocque" imagery of L., "The Healer of Hallucinations," Lois Smith, Solways visit, business of "explorations" being broken, Pasta, and Satie.
    - October1970, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 46-47)
      Includes references to: "The Mushroom Omelette," notes needing to be unscrambled, appeal of commonplace faces in the crowd, armchair astronomics, "The White Doe," and Nyack house dream.
    - November1970 (Box 9, Folder 48)
      Includes references to: image of Leila, "The Case/Dream of the Marvelous/Fabulous Fortune-Teller," Jackie Lane, "recouvrements" (concept of retrieving the irretrievable), and "(The) Slim Margin of Paradise."
    - December1970 (Box 9, Folder 49)
      Includes references to: Betsy, "The Cinnamon Screen," finding Weber/Debussy/Seroff in Joni file like Xmas present, passing of Dorothy Sayer, and bed musing.
    - January1971, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 50-51)
      Includes references to: Leila, Sitney and Mekas visit, hallucinations of a type that could be remembered, and neurotic sensibility (making of almost every decent moment a pretext for scribbling it down).
    - February1971 (Box 9, Folder 52)
      Includes references to: Corianne Marchand in Chloe from 5 to 7, "the sea in the veins," Marge Barker, and a finding in the Yeats book about Baudelaire.
    - March1971 (Box 9, Folder 53)
      Includes references to: "Schubert" dreaming, an immense soul-searching morning, discoveries for/regarding Leila, "headquarters" by stove, and the crows and the orange skin.
    - April1971 (Box 9, Folder 54)
      Includes references to: Harry Torczyner visit, "Char." returning to the fold, "Chariot d'Or," mixed hallucination, Leila, and cardinal.
    - May1971 (Box 9, Folder 55)
      Includes references to: Eagels "peace," Laurel/Ophelia, nasty hallucination, Robert's "Rabbit," marathon muddling through, the so-called "Laurel" ramblings, and Gabriel Faure.
    - June1971 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      Includes references to: futility of attempts at "making sense" in copy, honoring Robert, the past serving the present and the future, "too-muchness" of memory/nostalgia, and Ophelia's "owl."
    - July1971 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Includes references to: "a new heaven and a new earth," revelation in Breslin's, Betsy's "no-o," the Ostend, Bonnie Mirasola, "acrobate" context, the first "oeuf a la Russe" Rorschach, Brian O'Doherty, sun and moon collage, "a dress the color of time," Cygnus, "La Prestidigitateuse," "The Violinist," "Suzy Wong" file, Gogol "dreams," and a past immersed in books.
    - August1971, (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
      Includes references to: Rimbaud, Mother's letters, heritage of the quince, "Tea for the Tillerman" by Cat Stevens, Leila's arranging and sorting, Mother's birthday, the "edge of August," Rorschach ink drawings, "la funambule" (tightrope walker), new context of life, dwelling in "eterniday," St. Sebastian collage, Judith Richheimer, catharsis penning, and constellations.
    - September1971, (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
      Includes references to: being "stabbed by youth," Jackie Bisset file, Dulcinea passages from Don Quixote, "girls on bicycles," Judith as "la funambule," visit by Judith and her mother, Giraudoux, phenomenon of dreaming in context, obsessive craving for sweets, "Leo-Garden" collage, working in the "deep well," John Lennon and Yoko Ono on Dick Cavett, and Judith as "La Prestidigitateuse."
    - October1971 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      Includes references to: "The Sign of Jonah," "Arches of the Sky," dream sorting and arranging, workings of the mind, Picasso, and Queens College Life Class.
    - November1971 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Includes references to: Anne Baxter in The Razor's Edge, Virginia Dorazio visit, caches of material stashed around to draw upon, sudden "yield" of Mother's Xmas cards, Cooper Union, "Auriga" box in Beckman collection, "a dream of pennies," and resistance of life experience to recording.
    - December1971, (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 9-10)
      Includes references to: "The Landscape," Leila's call, Egan's 1949, visit of Octavio Paz with his wife and Dore Ashton, Caroline, devastating poignancy about condition of life, visit of Miss Thode, Joni dreaming, and "The Velvet Gentleman."
    - January1972, (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 11-12)
      Includes references to: Artemis, 1st Xmas with family in 4 years, rolling back the years in an incredible surprise renewal, dream of Mary Baker Eddy, exhaustively reviewing Betsy (Laurel) material, Francesca, and mounting Robert's "Rabbit" and "Standing Bear."
    - February1972, (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 13-14)
      Includes references to: "Penny Arcade exploration," "erotic" dreaming, "Famagouste," "in and out" of experience, equating hallucinations with "spirits" (with small "s"), Suzanne, a sudden inspiriting, "Mushroom Omelette," "Oeuf a la Russe," "Artemis" experience, organization of diaries, and "The Story of A."
    - March1972 (Box 10, Folder 15)
      Includes references to: purity of the "fille" aspect, recalling the "Sailor's Wife" of circa 1953, Mouse King Rorschach, preoccupation with "jeune fille" phenomenon, and a "borderline" atmosphere.
    - April1972 (Box 10, Folder 16)
      Includes references to: Lois, sequence of dream images after hour-long conversation with L., Lenke Hancock Wood, Aviary, a group of young people putting kitchen in order, and Helen Schiavo.
    - May1972 (Box 10, Folder 17)
      Includes references to: "Awake Dreaming," "A Confidence for Kittens," and going to dictionary and getting stuck on the "O"s.
    - June1972 (Box 10, Folder 18)
      Includes references to: Dream and Reality, Dorothy Dream context, conversation with a confidante, inner chambers of imagery, Edmund Wilson obituary, and "les dechirees - torn-ups - things torn up right and left."
    - July1972 (Box 10, Folder 19)
      Includes references to: Raymond Roussel, "acrobat" dream, first day of locust song, impossibility of "coherency" in this state, "oeufs a la Russe," prospect of the body restored after operation, and staying in Westhampton.
    - August1972 (Box 10, Folder 20)
      Includes references to: "amnesiac" feeling, Grandfather's letters, mixed happenings, "old story, but new situation," Dorothy, Bibliomania, Assemblage Greeting in Collage, "post-op" context, and Allegra.
    - September1972 (Box 10, Folder 21)
      Includes references to: J "taking over" from Laurel, Edith Wharton, Wayne Andrews, "The Grassy Slope," and "deus ex machina" type of dreaming.
    - October1972, (3 folders) (Box 10, Folder 22-24)
      Includes references to: arrival from Westhampton, trip to Northport, Lois, Gwen and family, status quo of art work, "Girl by a Tree" collage, Laurel, Marion Davies biography, Chaplin biography, "The Roving Gondola," and Allegra.
    - November1972 (Box 10, Folder 25)
      Includes references to: Lois, "a Cheeseburger for Paula," bottom falling out of dream business, Leila "storms," Daniel file (Joni), and "Caprice d'Ecureuil."
    - December1972, (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 26-27)
      Includes references to: "Tower of Pisa" dream of 9/13/69, first bus trip to Main St. since May, "The Harvest of Memory," Chirico revealed in the Ondine (Cerrito) "exploration," Nancy Grove, dream-haunting, memory-haunting, secondhand book locales of long ago, and the ad infinitum of dreaming.
  - Diary Notations,1941-1973, 3.2:
    Subseries consists of files of mostly undated notes, writings, and other material. The material in these files was most likely created at the same time and in the same way as the more formal diary entries. However, over time, this material came to be maintained separately in bulk files due to the lack of dates or consistent dating. Also included are a notebook, in which Cornell jotted down some notes, and some of Betty Cornell Benton's notes about the diaries, written while she was preparing Cornell's papers for donation.
    - 1941-1972, undated, (13 folders) (Box 10, Folder 28-40)
      Includes references to: "A Valentine for Susan Sontag," Jackie "exploration," Shirley MacLaine file, Carlotta Grisi, Cerrito, Gerard de Nerval, Dorazio, passing of Marilyn Monroe, C.S., Taglioni, sense of "eterniday," "Le Pays de Cocagne" collage, Pasadena exhibit, quince tree, St. Saens, Tilly Losch, "Hotel de l'Etoile" collage, Colombier annex to "Aviary," "Night Skies," "Nebula, the Powdered Sugar Princess Ballet," T. Toumanova, David Sontag, Carolee, Science and Health, Novalis, Swiss box, "the bird with the shoe-button eyes," Robert Indiana, Christine and Tony Curtis, secondhand books, all manner of bibliomania, the "funambule," and "Secret Life of a Sister of Tina."
    - Notes in Theme Tablet,1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 41)
    - Betty Cornell Benton's Notes on the Diaries,1973 (Box 10, Folder 42)
- Source Material, 1804-1972, Series 4:; (boxes 11-18, 25-28, OV 29; 8.5 linear feet)
  Series consists of Cornell's two-dimensional and textual source material and is largely comprised of files of clippings, notes, writings, stats, cutouts, and other printed material, stemming from his various artistic, research, writing, collecting, and collating activities. Some files are devoted to people and topics. Other files relate to specific art works, publishing projects, and exhibitions, as well as to his "explorations" in dance, music, art, science, and nature, among other topics, and his more personal "explorations" based on particular experiences and dreams. His typical practice involved accumulating massive amounts of material and information, which he would then collate into files, portfolios, or albums, continually adding to and refining them. Cornell seems to have used his source material as both raw material and inspiration for various creations, ranging from boxes and collages to design layouts for magazines and announcements for exhibitions of his work.
  Source material sheds light on Cornell's preoccupations with certain people, events, subjects, and motifs. It documents his work on certain art works, publishing ventures, and exhibition catalogues, as well as the evolution of some of his major "explorations" from original experience or idea to the completion of one or more art works, and the various stages of other "explorations" that may or may not have resulted in a finished product. Source material also documents the influence of his preoccupations and "explorations" on his various artistic and commercial projects, as well as some of the major themes that recur in his art work. Source material reflects Cornell's efforts to gain access to the past and bring it into the present; his wide-ranging interests and the linkages he found between seemingly unrelated ideas and things; his real and imaginary relationships with historical and contemporary figures (such as artists and ballerinas); his abiding interest in the symbolism of images and objects; and the interconnectedness of his many artistic and creative endeavors.
  The bulk of Cornell's source material, especially three-dimensional and non-textual material, can be found in the Joseph Cornell Study Center, Smithsonian American Art Museum, along with his library and record collection. Related material can also be found in Series 5: Ephemera and Artifacts.
  In the source material found amongst Cornell's papers, a distinction can be made between his files on people and topics, as well as between the files and portfolios. While he variously referred to his files as "dossiers," "compilations," "source files" "portfolios," and "albums" (among other terms), he seems to have primarily used the term "dossier" to refer to his files on people and the term "source files" more generally; in addition, his use of the term "portfolio" seems to refer more particularly to the material maintained in portfolio cases. Distinguishing between the different types of files and material while retaining some of Cornell's own terminology, the Source Material series is arranged into three subseries:
  4.1: Dossiers, 1941-1971
  4.2: Portfolios, 1831-1957
  4.3: Subject Source Files, 1804-1972
  The bulk of this series has been digitized with the exception of books, magazines and exhibition catalogs for artists other than Cornell; typically only covers, title pages, and/or relevant pages of these items have been digitized.
  - Dossiers, 1941-1971, 4.1:
    Subseries is comprised of Cornell's files ("dossiers") on people, including those in whom he had a particular interest and those with whom he identified or felt some sort of connection, whether real or imagined. People typically include historical and contemporary dancers (especially ballerinas), stage and film actresses, singers, artists, and writers. Dossiers are devoted to a particular individual and consist primarily of notes, writings, book and typed excerpts, prints, stats, clippings, correspondence, art work, and printed material.
    Dossiers generally relate to Cornell's "explorations" in ballet, music, art, literature, film, and theater, and to his particular preoccupations with ballerinas and opera singers from the Romantic era (including Marie Taglioni and Maria Malibran, respectively), with contemporary ballerinas and singers (including Renee "Zizi" Jeanmarie and Anna Moffo, respectively), with stage and film actresses (including Claire Bloom, Patty Duke, Jeanne Eagels, and Jennifer Jones), and with the work of other artists (including Johannes Vermeer) and writers. Dossiers document the development of these and other preoccupations, which typically began with some sort of encounter (such as seeing Duke perform in the play, Isle of Children, reading about Taglioni's performance in the ballet, La Sylphide, or coming across a reproduction of a Vermeer painting in a book or on a postcard) and came to involve extensive contemplation and writing. Dossiers also relate to certain art works and other creative projects arising from these particular "explorations" and preoccupations, including the various boxes and collages he made in tribute to Duke, Jeanmarie, Tilly Losch, and others, his self-publications (Maria and Bel Canto Pet) dedicated to the opera singers, Malibran and Grisi, and the planned brochure (La Retour de la Sylphide) dedicated to the ballerina, Taglioni.
    Dossiers document his personal contact with certain individuals with whom he was preoccupied (such as meeting Jeanmarie in her dressing room after a show and getting her autograph), and his imaginary involvement with others (such as the connection he felt with Bloom after discovering that, as a young girl, she had lived with her family in Forest Hills, New York during the same time period that he was working nearby). Dossiers also concern his relationships with other artists, including Lee Bontecou, Dorothy Coulter, Piero Dorazio, Yayoi Kusama, Tilly Losch (who was primarily known as a dancer and actress), and Robert Motherwell, as well as his relationship with the actor, Tony Curtis and his wife, Christine Kaufman. Many of these relationships are also documented in Cornell's correspondence.
    Files are arranged alphabetically according to the individual's surname.
    - Andersen, Hans Christian, 1954-1955, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Bloom, Claire, 1951-1968, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Bontecou, Lee, 1955-1971, undated, (4 folders) (Box 11, Folder 3-6)
    - [Bontecou], Nathalie, 1962, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Collins, Joan, 1958-1964, n.d (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Coulter, Dorothy, 1961, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Curtis, Tony and Christine (Kaufman), 1962-1970, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11, Folder 10-11)
    - Demongeot, Mylene, 1958-1960, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11, Folder 12-13)
    - Dorazio, Piero, 1951-1955, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Duke, Patty, 1962, 1967, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Duncan, Isadora, undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Eagels, Jeanne, 1963, undated (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Grisi, Giulia, [1956] (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Heiss, Carol, 1960-1961 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Jeanmarie, Renee "Zizi", 1949, undated, (3 folders) (Box 11, Folder 20-22)
    - Jones, Jennifer, 1945-1947, 1971, undated (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Kusama, Yayoi, 1964-1971, undated (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Lang, Pearl, 1957-1960, undated (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - Losch, Tilly, 1944, 1955-1958, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11, Folder 26-27)
      Includes a sketch and watercolors by Losch.
    - Malibran, Maria (See also Subseries 4.2), undated, (2 folders) (Box 11, Folder 28-29)
    - Mauri, Rosita, 1941-1948, undated (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - Moffo, Anna, 1965, undated (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - Motherwell, Robert, 1942-1953, undated, (3 folders) (Box 11, Folder 32-34)
    - Seitz, Dran and Tani, 1959-1961, undated (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - Sergava, Katharine, 1941-1947, undated (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - Swanson, Gloria, 1965, undated (Box 11, Folder 37)
    - Taglioni, Marie (See also Subseries 4.2), 1954-1956, undated (Box 11, Folder 38)
    - Vermeer, Johannes, 1948-1960, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11, Folder 39-40)
    - Welch, Mary, 1954-1958, undated (Box 11, Folder 41)
  - Portfolios, 1831-1957, 4.2:
    Subseries is comprised of portfolios devoted to two of Cornell's on-going "explorations," "Ondine (Cerrito)" and "Romantic Ballet." Portfolios consist of oversized and document-sized material, including notes, book and typed excerpts, stats, clippings, lithograph portraits, prints, sheet music, writings, and other printed material. Portfolio titles are drawn from the inscriptions on the outside of each portfolio case. Cornell more than likely compiled this material in much the same way as that in his other files, though he ended up storing and maintaining it separately due perhaps to the size of certain items.